<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>OPeNDAP Documentation</sitename>
    <dbname>wikidb</dbname>
    <base>https://docs.opendap.org/index.php/Home</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.38.4</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">OPeNDAP Documentation</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">OPeNDAP Documentation talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>UserGuideChapter2</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>182</id>
    <revision>
      <id>1148</id>
      <timestamp>2007-09-25T02:36:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Yuan</username>
        <id>8</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>New page: =Using OPeNDAP=   A user uses OPeNDAP with an OPeNDAP client program.  This client program may have been acquired by the user (for example, the OPeNDAP Matlab and IDL graphic user interfac...</comment>
      <origin>1148</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="18442" sha1="ksfoyebl2dzb40xibxxnsit4it2v76v" xml:space="preserve">=Using OPeNDAP=


A user uses OPeNDAP with an OPeNDAP client program.  This client program may
have been acquired by the user (for example, the OPeNDAP Matlab and IDL
graphic user interfaces, or Ferret, a freeware data analysis package
each use OPeNDAP for data access), or may be a program converted to
use the OPeNDAP library for data access (see ([http://www &lt;cite&gt; opd-client&lt;/cite&gt;]).

In either case, there are a set of issues that must be addressed in
order to use a program to access data through OPeNDAP.  The issues can be
classed into two groups.  One set of issues involves configuring the
system to provide OPeNDAP with the helper applications and environment
variables it requires.  The other set concerns the manner in which a
user communicates with an OPeNDAP server.  We cover this first

==How OPeNDAP Finds Data==



Once linked to the
OPeNDAP libraries, an OPeNDAP client created from an existing program will
work exactly as before when run using local files.  However, a user
can also specify an OPeNDAP Uniform Resource Locator (URL) to indicate
some data file on a remote host machine.  When the program receives
this URL, the OPeNDAP libraries will recognize it as remote data, and
issue a network request for the data.  If a user has also installed
an OPeNDAP server on the local machine, then local data may be accessed
either through their local filenames or their OPeNDAP URL.

A URL is simply a unique name for some Internet resource.
The [[Image:opd-client,fig,url-parts]] shows the parts of a
typical OPeNDAP URL.

\begin{figure}[h]
\texorhtml
{\small
${}\overbrace{&gt;dncview}^{Program}
\overbrace"http}^{Protocol"://
\overbrace"dods.gso.uri.edu}^{Machine Name"/
\overbrace"cgi-bin/nph-nc}^{Server"/
\overbrace"data}^{Directory"/
\overbrace"fnoc1.nc}^{Filename"/
\overbrace".das}^{URL Suffix}$"
{\begin{vcode}{cb}
&gt;dncview http://dods.gso.uri.edu/cgi-bin/nph-nc/data/fnoc1.nc.das

^     ^      ^                        ^      ^    ^        ^

|     |      |                        |      |    |        |
Program  |      |                        |      |    |        |
Protocol--      |                        |      |    |        |
Machine Name-----                        |      |    |        |
Server------------------------------------      |    |        |
Directory----------------------------------------    |        |
Filename----------------------------------------------        |
URL Suffix-----------------------------------------------------
\end{vcode}}
\caption{Parts of an OPeNDAP URL (without a constraint expression)}

\end{figure}

The parts of the URL are:

&lt;blockquote&gt;

; protocol :


The protocol of an Internet request may be thought of as the kind
of conversation the client expects to have with the target machine.
For example, a web browser like Netscape Navigator wants to find
a server that can return hypertext documents, while an ftp client
wants to find a server that can understand file transfer requests. A
web browser equipped to display hypertext documents will specify
&lt;font color='green'&gt;http&lt;/font&gt; as the protocol for its conversation, and hope that the target
machine has an &lt;font color='green'&gt;httpd&lt;/font&gt; daemon listening.

; host : The host name in a URL is simply the
Internet address of the host machine running whatever server can
reply to the specified protocol.

; server : A special feature of the &lt;font color='green'&gt;httpd&lt;/font&gt; server process is
that it may be configured to execute Common Gateway Interface (CGI)
programs  upon receipt of a properly specified URL. This is used, for example, by
Internet search engines that ask a user to fill out a form. The CGI
specification will be specific to the server in question, and the
part of the URL that follows the CGI name is passed to the CGI upon
invocation. This data may include a file name, but it may as easily
be some arbitrary string of instructions. The OPeNDAP server is simply
a set of CGI scripts executed on demand by the &lt;font color='green'&gt;httpd&lt;/font&gt; server.
Here, the OPeNDAP server is represented by a CGI script called
&lt;font color='green'&gt;nph-nc&lt;/font&gt;.

; filename :  If a CGI is not
specified, the part of the URL after the host name is simply the
name of a file that is to be returned to the inquiring browser.  If
a CGI is specified, the file is given to the program as its
argument.

; URL suffix :  If you are issuing an OPeNDAP request
from a non-OPeNDAP client, such as a web browser, you can specify the
type of request by appending a suffix to the URL.  Different
suffixes demand different services from the server.  The different
services are listed in ([http://www &lt;cite&gt; opd-client,services&lt;/cite&gt;]).  If you
are using OPeNDAP from an OPeNDAP client, or a client program adapted to
use the OPeNDAP DAP library, you do not need to use a URL suffix.  For
example, to use OPeNDAP from Matlab, with the Matlab GUI or
command-line clients, you do not need to use a suffix.  To use OPeNDAP
from a simple web browser like Netscape Navigator, you will need to
use a suffix.

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The URL in [[Image:opd-client,fig,url-parts]] shows a client
request to the &lt;font color='green'&gt;httpd&lt;/font&gt; server on the machine
&lt;font color='green'&gt;dods.gso.uri.edu&lt;/font&gt;, for a netCDF dataset (specified by the
&lt;font color='green'&gt;nph-nc} in the \lit{cgi-bin&lt;/font&gt; directory) contained in a file
called &lt;font color='green'&gt;fnoc1.nc}.  Upon receiving this URL, the \lit{httpd&lt;/font&gt;
server executes the specified OPeNDAP server module (&lt;font color='green'&gt;nph-nc&lt;/font&gt;), which
retrieves the file is in a directory called &lt;font color='green'&gt;data&lt;/font&gt; relative to
wherever the &lt;font color='green'&gt;httpd&lt;/font&gt; server looks for its data\footnote{The only

part of the URL whose spelling is not at the discretion of the
administrator of the host machine is the &lt;font color='green'&gt;http&lt;/font&gt;, and the
&lt;font color='green'&gt;nph-&lt;/font&gt; at the beginning of the CGI script name. Even the
&lt;font color='green'&gt;nc&lt;/font&gt;, indicating netCDF, can be changed, although for clarity's
sake, we hope people won't do so.  Incidentally, the &lt;font color='green'&gt;nph-&lt;/font&gt; is a
relic, dating from the early days of the World Wide Web and the
first hypertext protocol standards.  It stands for "Non-Parsing
Header" (See the CGI 1.1 Standard for more information.), and is
the only way to pass data through many httpd servers unparsed.}.

OPeNDAP URLs can get somewhat more complicated than this simple
description.  In particular, they can contain "constraint
expressions" that limit a request to data satisfying a set of
conditions, and they can contain requests to specific OPeNDAP services,
besides the data delivery service suggested here.  Constraint
expressions are described in more detail in
([http://www &lt;cite&gt; opd-client,constraint&lt;/cite&gt;]), while the array of services
provided by OPeNDAP servers are described in
([http://www &lt;cite&gt; opd-client,services&lt;/cite&gt;]).

===Security===
Some OPeNDAP data providers will choose to control access to some or all
of their data.  When you request data from one of these servers, the
OPeNDAP client  will prompt you for a username and password.  If you want
to avoid the prompt, you can make the OPeNDAP URL even more baroque by
embedding a username and password in it, like this:

\begin{vcode}{sib}
http://user:password@www.dods.org/nph-dods/etc...
\end{vcode}


==The OPeNDAP Services==

Up to now, we have treated the OPeNDAP server as if it has only one
service: providing data to clients who ask for it.  It is true that
this is the most important service a server provides.  However, it is
also true that the server provides several other services besides
that.  In fact, fulfilling a request for data actually requires three
separate requests from the client, using three different services of
the OPeNDAP server.

The services requested from an OPeNDAP server are specified in a suffix
appended to the URL described in
[[Image:opd-client,fig,url-parts]].  Depending on the suffix
supplied, the server will provide one of these services:


&lt;blockquote&gt;

; Data Attribute : This service returns the entire data

attribute structure for the given dataset. This is a text file

describing the attributes of each data quantity in that dataset.

(See ([http://www &lt;cite&gt; data,das&lt;/cite&gt;]) for more information about data

attributes.)  This service is activated when the

server receives a URL ending with &lt;font color='green'&gt;.das&lt;/font&gt;.


; Data Descriptor : This service returns the entire data descriptor
structure for the given dataset. This is a text file describing the
structure of the variables in the dataset. (See
([http://www &lt;cite&gt; data,dds&lt;/cite&gt;]) for more information about data descriptors.)
This service is activated when the server receives a URL ending with
&lt;font color='green'&gt;.dds&lt;/font&gt;.

; OPeNDAP Data : This service returns the actual data requested by
a given URL. This is not a text file, but is encoded as a
Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME) document.  This service
is activated when the server receives a URL ending with &lt;font color='green'&gt;.dods&lt;/font&gt;

; ASCII Data : This service returns an ASCII representation of
the requested data.  This can make the data available to a wide
variety of browser programs.  This service is activated when the
server receives a URL ending with &lt;font color='green'&gt;.asc} or \lit{.ascii&lt;/font&gt;.

; \ifh : When the server receives a URL ending in
&lt;font color='green'&gt;.html&lt;/font&gt;, it produces an HTML form containing information from
the dataset that you can use to construct a sensible URL with which
to request OPeNDAP data.  The \ifh is also triggered when the OPeNDAP
server receives a URL that references a directory instead of a file.

; Information :  This service returns information about
the server and dataset, in human-readable HTML form.  The returned
document may include information about both the data server itself
(e.g. server functions implemented), and the dataset referenced in
the URL.  The server administrator determines what information is
returned in response to such a request.  This service is activated
when the server receives a URL ending with &lt;font color='green'&gt;.info&lt;/font&gt;. See
([http://www &lt;cite&gt; sec,document-data&lt;/cite&gt;]) for more information about how to
configure the information service.

; Version : This service returns the version information for the
OPeNDAP server software running on the server.  This service is
triggered by a URL ending with &lt;font color='green'&gt;.ver&lt;/font&gt;.

; Help : This service returns some help text in response to an
improperly specified URL.  This service is triggered by a URL ending
in any suffix that is not recognized by the OPeNDAP server.

&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;A request for data from an OPeNDAP client will generally make three
different service requests, for data attributes, data descriptors, and
for data.  The prepackaged OPeNDAP clients do this for you, so you may
not be aware that three requests are made for each URL.  That is, an OPeNDAP client may accept an OPeNDAP URL specifying some data, such as the
one shown in [[Image:opd-client,fig,url-parts]].  In this case, the
OPeNDAP client library (such as nc-dods) will accept the input URL, and
append the different suffixes to that URL, making three distinct
requests to the OPeNDAP server.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===\ifh===


Each OPeNDAP server implements a service called the \ifh .  This is a way
to use a standard Web client, such as Netscape, to get information
about the data served by a specific server.\footnote{The \ifh is only

available for servers later than version 3.1.} The \ifh has two
modes of operation: the directory level and the file level.

If an OPeNDAP URL references a directory instead of a file on the server
machine, the server produces a listing similar to that shown in
[[Image:opd-client,fig,ifh-dir]].

\figureplace{\ifh - Directory Level}{htbp}
{opd-client,fig,ifh-dir}{ifh-dir.ps}{ifh-dir.gif}{}

Clicking on a dataset shown in the directory-level listing
will produce an HTML form similar to the one in
[[Image:opd-client,fig,ifh]].  The top line in the window ("Data
URL") shows a URL that makes a request for an OPeNDAP dataset.  The
windows below it show the variables that make up the dataset.  You can
edit the form to select the data you'd like to see from this dataset,
and the \ifh will edit the Data URL so that it only requests the data
you are interested in.  When done, you can push the "ASCII" button,
to see an ASCII representation of the data you've requested.  Netscape
cannot handle binary data, so if you
want to use the binary data, you should copy the URL in the Data URL
window to the OPeNDAP client you'd like to use.

\figureplace{\ifh}{htbp}
{opd-client,fig,ifh}{ifh.ps}{ifh.gif}{}

==Using an OPeNDAP Program==


There are some
configuration issues a user must consider in order to use an OPeNDAP
client application program. There is a short list of software that is
required for some of the advanced features of OPeNDAP, and some
environment variables that control the execution of the OPeNDAP software.
For a piece of software that has been converted to use OPeNDAP, after
these conditions are satisfied, the program will run in the same
manner it ran before. Aside from network delays, the user should not
be able to tell that they are accessing data from the Internet.


Finally, though it may seem unnecessary to mention, in order for an OPeNDAP client application to communicate with an OPeNDAP server, the
computer running the OPeNDAP client must be connected to the Internet.

===Requirements===

In order to use of some of the features of the OPeNDAP core software, a
user's computer must have some additional software installed, and
available on the user's &lt;font color='green'&gt;PATH&lt;/font&gt;, in
&lt;font color='green'&gt;&amp;#36;DODS_ROOT/bin} or \lit{&amp;#36;DODS_ROOT/etc&lt;/font&gt;.


\indc{system

configuration}


*The &lt;font color='green'&gt;wish} {Tcl}}/{\ind{Tk&lt;/font&gt; interpreter (or whatever
program is indicated by the &lt;font color='green'&gt;DODS_GUI&lt;/font&gt; environment variable) is
used by the "GUI manager" to provide a progress indicator
that displays the status of a pending data request as it is being
processed. It is also used by the error reporting system to display
error message received from the server.  \tbd{and by the data
locator, to display information and query the user}
*The &lt;font color='green'&gt;gzip}&lt;/font&gt; program, the \ind{GNU compression
software, is used to decompress data messages received from an OPeNDAP
server. If this program is not installed, the OPeNDAP core software
tells the server not to send compressed messages, so data may still
be received.  However, having the compression software installed and
available will increase the data transfer rate.

The required software, like OPeNDAP itself, is free software. Refer to
\appref{install} for information about acquiring that software.

===Environment Variables===

After successfully relinking an application program with the OPeNDAP
libraries, there is a short list of environment variables that
may be defined.  Only &lt;font color='green'&gt;DODS_ROOT&lt;/font&gt; is required. The other three
variables are only used to override default values controlling the GUI
manager process. Most users may safely ignore them.

&lt;blockquote&gt;

; &lt;font color='green'&gt;DODS_ROOT&lt;/font&gt; :  indicates the root directory of the OPeNDAP
software. The OPeNDAP core software must be able to locate utilities
that are located in this directory tree. \indc{environment
variables!DODS_ROOT}

; &lt;font color='green'&gt;DODS_GUI&lt;/font&gt; : can contain the name of the program used by the
\new{GUI manager}.  A user might wish to change this variable to
point to a "safe" Tcl/Tk interpreter; whatever program is used
here must be able to process Tcl and Tk commands.  The default value
is the &lt;font color='green'&gt;wish&lt;/font&gt; program.   \indc{environment
variables!DODS_GUI}

; &lt;font color='green'&gt;DODS_GUI_INIT&lt;/font&gt; : indicates the name of any initialization
command required by the "GUI manager". The default
initialization string executes the Tcl program in
&lt;font color='green'&gt;&amp;#36;DODS_ROOT/etc/dods_gui.tc1&lt;/font&gt;.
\indc{environment
variables!DODS_GUI_INIT}

; &lt;font color='green'&gt;DODS_USE_GUI&lt;/font&gt; : may be used to turn off the GUI manager. Set
the value of this variable to &lt;font color='green'&gt;no&lt;/font&gt;, and the progress indicator
and the error message windows will not be displayed.


&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The user has substantial control over the GUI manager. You can
change the program that listens for GUI commands from &lt;font color='green'&gt;wish&lt;/font&gt; to
anything else, and you can actually change the action of the GUI
commands by editing the Tcl code in the files &lt;font color='green'&gt;dods_gui.tcl&lt;/font&gt;,
&lt;font color='green'&gt;error.tcl}, and \lit{progress.tcl&lt;/font&gt;. (These are in the
&lt;font color='green'&gt;&amp;#36;DODS_ROOT/etc&lt;/font&gt; directory.)  However, editing these files and
variables will not change the form of the messages from the OPeNDAP
server, and from the core software that are meant to invoke these
programs. In other words, the user may mess with these, but must be
careful to leave the GUI manager in a form that will be able to
process the messages it receives.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

===The Error System===



The GUI manager is used to display error messages
to the user. The messages themselves will vary with the server
implementation. Refer to the documentation of the particular server,
or consult the server's &lt;font color='green'&gt;info&lt;/font&gt; Service (See
([http://www &lt;cite&gt; opd-server,service&lt;/cite&gt;]).), for a list of the error messages
that might be issued by a particular server.  \tbd{As error codes are
finalized, they should be included in an Appendix of this document,
and a pointer to them included here.}

===Temporary Files===


Using an OPeNDAP client application will
create a number of temporary files. They are created with the
&lt;font color='green'&gt;tmpnam()&lt;/font&gt; function, so their names will correspond to the rules
for that function on your system (See the manual page for
&lt;font color='green'&gt;tmpnam(3)}, or type \lit{man tmpnam&lt;/font&gt; for more information.)
During normal operation, OPeNDAP will delete the temporary files it
creates as it goes. However, if execution of the OPeNDAP client is
somehow interrupted, these files may remain, and will have to be
deleted by hand.


&lt;!-- EDIT TEMPLATE DOCUMENTATION BELOW THIS LINE --&gt;
This template will add tagged articles to [[:UserGuide1]].</text>
      <sha1>ksfoyebl2dzb40xibxxnsit4it2v76v</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
