<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>OPeNDAP Documentation</sitename>
    <dbname>wikidb</dbname>
    <base>https://docs.opendap.org/index.php/Home</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.38.4</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">OPeNDAP Documentation</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">OPeNDAP Documentation talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>DAP4: DDX Grammar</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>732</id>
    <revision>
      <id>9292</id>
      <parentid>9291</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-09-04T16:40:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jimg</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Differences with DAP4 xsd Grammar */</comment>
      <origin>9292</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4492" sha1="iez6ireioax9i96hycberwj2xnhvf95" xml:space="preserve">[[OPULS_Development| &lt;&lt;back to OPULS Development]]

'''Version: 1.0'''

At the end of this document are instructions for accessing and testing a formal grammar for the DAP4 DDX using the Relax-NG schema language. I constructed it without any reference to any other explicit or implicit grammars so I could record my ideas. I have since modified it based examining the implied grammar in page [[DAP4: Data Model]] and from comments from others and from a comparison with the xsd grammar.

'''NOTE''': [[User:Jimg|Jimg]] 14:19, 28 August 2012 (PDT) There is a copy of the dap4.rng file in subversion at https://scm.opendap.org/svn/trunk/xml/dap/. I think that version is more recent than the dropbox files referenced by this document.

== Differences with DAP4 xsd Grammar ==
I converted the xsd-based grammar
https://scm.opendap.org/trac/browser/trunk/xml/dap/dap4.xsd
to an equivalent relax-ng grammar.
http://dl.dropbox.com/u/53929684/xsd.rng (now also at https://scm.opendap.org/svn/trunk/xml/dap/dap4.rng)


One major difference I see is in dimension handling.
# I just used the name "dimension" rather than "shareddimension"; For me, all dimensions (except anonymous ones and variable length) are shared.
# The xsd separates out scalars from arrays. I always allowed the dimensions for a variable to be optional to handle the scalar case.
# I attempted to be as consistent as possible, so I allowed any type including sequences &lt;del&gt;and structures&lt;/del&gt; to be dimensioned.
# &lt;del&gt;The dimensions of a variable are currently specified in the rng grammar as an attribute named "dimensions" associated with "variables": e.g. dimensions="dr d1".&lt;br/&gt; Previously I used this:&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;
&lt;dimensions&gt;
&lt;dimension name="dr"/&gt;
&lt;dimension name="d1"/&gt;
&lt;/dimensions&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt; But this seemed kind of verbose.&lt;/del&gt;

Other differences:
# The Dataset element in the xsd has a couple of extra attributes. I added these.
# The xsd appears to allow attributes to themselves have attributes. This needs discussion.
# I forgot enumerations and opaque. I added them.
# The URL basetype is in the xsd. What is the justification for keeping it?
# It appears that the Dataset contains a top level &lt;group&gt; declaration; I chose to treat the Dataset itself as the top-level group.
# Attribute declarations appear to have their own "namespace" attribute. Not sure why this is needed.
# I do not understand the purpose of the "NewAttribute" attribute.
# &lt;del&gt;The Grid issue, of course&lt;/del&gt; There are still some minor differences in representing coordinate variables.
# The xsd represents attribute values thus:
 &lt;Attribute name="a"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;...&lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;...&lt;/value&gt;
 &lt;/Attribute&gt;
: I provided an alternate form when there is only one value:
 &lt;Attribute name="a" value="..."/&gt;
: and I chose to use attributes in the multi-valued case because I prefer not to use elements with content unless really necessary. So I represented the above as this.
 &lt;Attribute name="a"&gt;
   &lt;Value value="..."/&gt;
   &lt;Value value="..."/&gt;
 &lt;/Attribute&gt;

There are also some minor differences.
# &lt;del&gt;Element names (e.g. &lt;structure&gt;) are capitalized in the xsd grammar&lt;/del&gt; I modified the rng grammar to capitalize.
# There is an issue of interleaving of definitions, or equivalently, what elements must occur in a fixed order. 
# Where should attributes be legal? I think the rng grammar and the xsd grammar agree on this: putting them almost everywhere, but it needs discussion.

Other differences:
# &lt;del&gt;I temporarily suppressed OtherXML because it did not translate correctly&lt;/del&gt; Fixed.
# I dropped Blobtype; I fail to see the need for this.

=== Testing the Relax-NG Grammar ===
'''NOTE''': See subversion as described at the top of this page for more recent versions of the grammar.

You will need to copy three files:
# dap4.rng - this is the grammar file; it uses the Relax-NG schema language (http://relaxng.org/).&lt;br/&gt;This can be obtained from http://dl.dropbox.com/u/53929684/dap4.rng
# test.xml - this is a test file, that I am growing to cover the whole grammar.&lt;br/&gt;This can be obtained from http://dl.dropbox.com/u/53929684/test.xml
# jing.jar - Jing is a validator that takes the grammar and a test file and checks that the test file conforms to the grammar.&lt;br/&gt;This can be obtained from http://dl.dropbox.com/u/53929684/jing.jar.

To use it, do the command:
 java -jar jing.jar dap4.rng test.xml
No output is produced if the validation succeeds, otherwise, error messages are produced.

''-Dennis Heimbigner''</text>
      <sha1>iez6ireioax9i96hycberwj2xnhvf95</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
