<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>OPeNDAP Documentation</sitename>
    <dbname>wikidb</dbname>
    <base>https://docs.opendap.org/index.php/Home</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.38.4</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">OPeNDAP Documentation</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">OPeNDAP Documentation talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>RDH Catalog Organization</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>492</id>
    <revision>
      <id>4259</id>
      <parentid>4258</parentid>
      <timestamp>2009-05-08T17:03:34Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Ndp</username>
        <id>2</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* ''lastModified'' Attribute */</comment>
      <origin>4259</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="5557" sha1="lihukelrohgr0ea8nhlm3ptq0o40tjv" xml:space="preserve">== Definitions ==

; Catalog
: A collection of data holdings on a DAP server. This collection may be flat (a simple list) or it may be hierarchically organized.

; Navigation URL
: A URL that returns an HTML document that when rendered allows a human to navigate the catalog of data holdings on a DAP server. 

; Catalog URL
; Inventory URL
: A URL that returns a machine readable catalog (aka inventory) of data holdings on a DAP server. The most common of these is a THREDDS catalog URL.

;Resource URL
: The globally (like internet globally) unique address of a resource. 
: For example:
:* http://test.opendap.org:8080/opendap/ - refers to an HTML document that provides a human readable inventory of the top level of holdings in a Hyrax server.
:* http://test.opendap.org:8080/opendap/data/nc/fnoc1.nc.dds - refers to a DDS, a machine readable document describing the syntactic structure of a DAP data source.
:* 

;Resource ID
: The locally unique ID of a resource. Locally here means within a particular server.
:  &lt;br&gt;
: In the BES that means the catalog name followed by the path in that catalog to the resource. 
: For example:
:* ''/rdh/dataSourceOne'' - is the resource ID of the resource called ''dataSourceOne'' in the catalog called ''rdh''
:* ''/catalog/data/nc/fnoc1.nc'' - is the resource ID of the resource called ''data/nc/fnoc1.nc'' in the catalog called ''catalog''
:* ''/data/nc/fnoc1.nc'' - is the resource ID of the resource called ''data/nc/fnoc1.nc'' in the default catalog (which is confusingly named ''catalog'')
:  &lt;br&gt;
: In Hyrax that means the all of the stuff after the protocol, server name, and context name. 
: In the URL ''&lt;nowiki&gt;http://test.opendap.org:8080/opendap/data/nc/fnoc1.nc.dds&lt;/nowiki&gt;'' the resource ID is: ''/data/nc/fnoc1.nc.dds''

; Data access URL
: A URL that returns DAP data product (DDS, DDX, DAS, DataDDS, etc.) from a holding on a DAP server.

== RDH Catalog ==

The RDH will need to have it's own catalog in the BES catalog system, by default it should be called '''rdh'''. It can be remapped to a different name via the BES configuration file if needed (see below).

In order to populate its catalog the  RDH needs to be able to provide a representation of its data holdings. Since the RDH relies on a simple list of ODBC Data Sources in its configuration file (See the [[Adding the RDH to the BES | RDH Configuration Use Case]] and the [[RDH handles bes:showCatalog request | RDH Catalog Use Case ]]) it's catalog is flat, just the simple list of Data Source names. 

In BES speak that means that RDH catalog contains no sub collections, aka containers, aka child catalogs. The RDH holdings can and should be represented as a simple list of DAP data sets. Each of these data sets has a DDS/DDX/DAS representation that can be accessed in the typical DAP manner. When responding to a bes:showCatalog request the RDH should return a catalog composed of a top level dataset that contains a list of dataset elements each of which has a ''node'' attribute whose value is false and (at minimum) a child bes:serviceRef element with a value of "dap" :

  &lt;response xmlns="http://xml.opendap.org/ns/bes/1.0#" reqID="some_unique_value"&gt;
    &lt;showCatalog&gt;
        &lt;dataset catalog="rdh" count="13" lastModified="2009-03-24T19:02:46" name="/" node="true" size="578"&gt;
            &lt;dataset catalog="catalog" lastModified="-1" name="dataSourceOne" node="false" size="-1"&gt;
                &lt;serviceRef&gt;dap&lt;/serviceRef&gt;
            &lt;/dataset&gt;
            &lt;dataset catalog="catalog" lastModified="-1" name="dataSourceTwo" node="false" size="-1"&gt;
                &lt;serviceRef&gt;dap&lt;/serviceRef&gt;
            &lt;/dataset&gt;
            &lt;dataset catalog="catalog" lastModified="-1" name="dataSourceThree" node="false" size="-1"&gt;
                &lt;serviceRef&gt;dap&lt;/serviceRef&gt;
            &lt;/dataset&gt;
        &lt;/dataset&gt;
    &lt;/showCatalog&gt;
 &lt;/response&gt;

==== ''size'' Attribute ====

What does the size of the dataset mean in this context? 
* Is it the aggregate size of all of the holdings in the Data Source? 
* Can that be easily determined through the ODBC API?

If determining the size of the holding is a sensible activity (there is a  decent API, it's time efficient, etc) then we should do it. Otherwise return a "-1" to indicate that the value is not known.

==== ''lastModified'' Attribute ====

What does the last modified date of the dataset mean in this context? 
* Is it the the last time time that data was added to the Data Source? 
* Is is the last time the Data Source definition was changed?  
* What happens if the Data Source defines a subset of the available holdings in the underlying RDBMS?
** Is last modified then the last time that one of the tables or views in the RDBMS made are available through the Data Source was changed?
* Can that be easily determined through the ODBC API?

If determining the last modified time of the holding is a sensible activity (there is a  decent API, it's time efficient, etc) then we should do it. Otherwise we should return a "-1" to indicate that the value is not known. (&lt;font color=red&gt;Is that right? What's the missing value for this in the BES XML API?&lt;/font&gt;)


== Hyrax/BES catalog integration issues ==

Currently the BES supports multiple catalogs. Hyrax does not. Hyrax relies solely on the default BES catalog. In order for the RDH to successfully integrate into Hyrax the various BES catalogs must be exposed through the OLFS (and thus Hyrax).

&lt;u&gt;'''[[Fixing the (currently) broken Hyrax catalogs  | This work is being discussed and managed here.]]'''&lt;/u&gt;</text>
      <sha1>lihukelrohgr0ea8nhlm3ptq0o40tjv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
