<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>OPeNDAP Documentation</sitename>
    <dbname>wikidb</dbname>
    <base>https://docs.opendap.org/index.php/Home</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.38.4</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">OPeNDAP Documentation</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">OPeNDAP Documentation talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Hyrax - Create BES Module</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>125</id>
    <revision>
      <id>9963</id>
      <parentid>9962</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-10-29T16:01:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jimg</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* What gets created? */</comment>
      <origin>9963</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="4307" sha1="c9e9u43eqjkuoh9ncn3sqytpxc1z5f4" xml:space="preserve">Building a new OPeNDAP BES Module

This document will cover the creation of a new BES module using the besCreateModule script. It is quite simple to create a new module, once you understand the power of the BES framework.

For more information on the server architecture, please refer to the document BES_Server_Architecture.doc. For more information on configuration the BES server, please refer to the document BES_Configuration.doc.

-----
=Creating a new OPeNDAP module=
We have provided you with a script that can build code that will immediately compile. This script will create source code files that you will eventually add your code to, and some code that will not need to be changed, as well as configuration scripts and make files.

-----
==Using the besCreateModule script==
The besCreateModule script will ask you, the developer, a few simple questions in order to create some default source code. The good thing is, once this code is written you can run make and your code will build. Of course, it won't do much because you need to write specific code to provide OPeNDAP objects for the requested data. There are no parameters to the script, so, from the command line, do the following:

 % ./besCreateModule

The script will ask the user the following questions:

 Enter server type, e.g. cedar, fits, netcdf:

So, for example, if you are providing cedar data, you would respond with cedar. Or, if you are providing hdf5 data you would respond hdf5.

The second question is:

 Enter C++ class prefix, e.g. Cedar, Fits, Netcdf:

There are some C++ class files that are created that need a prefix. What do you want that prefix to be? For example, if you are writing a new cedar server then the prefix could be Cedar. We suggest that the first character be uppercase, but does not need to be. Another example, if you are providing hdf5 data, then you could respond HDF5.

The third question is:

 Enter responses handled by this server (das dds data):
 (space separated. help and version are added for you, no need to include them here)

So, if your module will provide OPeNDAP DAS, DDS, and Data objects (and DDX) then you would simply hit enter (default is das dds data). Here is where some of the new extensibility comes in. You could provide a new way of viewing the data. For example, Cedar provides four new response types, tab, flat, info and stream. We will explain this in more detail in another document. For cedar, then, you would respond with 'das dds data tab flat info stream.' If you are not providing any views of data, then you would enter 'none'.

And the final question is:

 Enter new commands you are implementing:

If you are writing new commands for this module, then you would enter them here. New commands would be something like "say hello to world;", something that the BES has not implemented.

-----

==What gets created?==
Once you have answered these questions, then there are a bunch of files that get created. Let's say that you enter 'hdf', 'HDF', and accept the default for response types (das dds data). The files created are:

 HDFModule.cc
 HDFModule.h
 HDFRequestHandler.cc
 HDFRequestHandler.h
 HDFResponseNames.h
 Makefile.am
 configure.ac
 bes.conf

If you specified new response types then for each new response type two files will be created:

 HDF&lt;response_type&gt;ResponseHandler.cc
 HDF&lt;response_type&gt;ResponseHandler.h

If you specified new commands then for each new command four files will be created:

 HDF&lt;command_name&gt;Command.cc
 HDF&lt;command_name&gt;Command.h
 HDF&lt;command_name&gt;ResponseHandler.cc
 HDF&lt;command_name&gt;ResponseHandler.h

A new configuration directory is also created, conf, that holds build configuration files and information.

The besCreateModule script then runs autoreconf, configure, and make. The new code will compile and build the BES module library that can be dynamically loaded into the BES. We are assuming that you have already built the OPeNDAP code (libdap and bes)

And that's it!

Now the task is to write the code that will actually build your responses. Of course, you are free to add whatever you need to the configure.ac file and Makefile.am file in order to build your new module. You'll need to add information about libraries and includes that your project will need.

[[Category:BES Modules|Create BES Module]]</text>
      <sha1>c9e9u43eqjkuoh9ncn3sqytpxc1z5f4</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
