<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>OPeNDAP Documentation</sitename>
    <dbname>wikidb</dbname>
    <base>https://docs.opendap.org/index.php/Home</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.38.4</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">OPeNDAP Documentation</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">OPeNDAP Documentation talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>GuideLines</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>767</id>
    <revision>
      <id>7531</id>
      <parentid>7530</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-03-07T05:06:10Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jimg</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Software Development Rules FAQ */</comment>
      <origin>7531</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="3812" sha1="dosy2w8bu4dkgpi8zvlminjxaff7d46" xml:space="preserve">== Software Development Rules FAQ ==

'''Are there any rules to follow when performing development tasks?'''

Yes, there are several rules that must be followed in order for the tracking
and control system to function effectively and to permit work to move from
person to person in a seamless manner. If you take into account that you are
communicating and presenting your work to other team members as you submit
it, then you are likely to be following the spirit of these rules.

== Ticket Rules ==

'''Avoid performing work without a ticket'''

If you feel you need to briefly work without a ticket (one day
max) while using your own judgment to chase down an issue you run into, you
can do so. This should not be a terribly frequent practice. Please consider
having a ticket added retroactively in such cases, particularly if you want
your work to be reflected in the reports that come from Trac.

'''When you start work on a Ticket, accept it via the Action area at the bottom of the ticket'''

It is ok to accept the ticket and stop work as other priorities compete.
This gives management a good perception of which tasks are currently being
actively pursued.

'''When done with the work associated with a ticket, close it promptly'''

For those tickets that are for bug fixes or new features, immediately after
checking in the associated code on the trunk is ideal.

'''Preference ticket notations over scratch paper and/or memory when keeping
notes on your progress for a task'''

Notating tickets frequently allows work to be seemlessly reassigned to
another person in mid-stream. It makes the team more flexible and allows us
to take better advantage of each others strengths.

'''Use the Category ticket property in a consistent manner when adding a new
ticket or when changing the category of a ticket.'''

From left to right in the Ticket Property area, we have Bug, Feature and
Task categories. Set the property according to the left-most category that
it fits into. If it is a bug, classify it as such. Otherwise, if it is a
feature classify it as such. If it is neither of those categories, classify
it as a Task. This keeps the categorization both consistent and compatible
with the automatic generation of data for the Release Description Document
at release time.

== Source Code Repository Rules ==

'''Do not use the selective locking feature of Subversion's, except for documents.'''

Documents are stored under /doc - the designated place for sharing and
versioning documents via subversion.

'''Enter appropriately descriptive text describing changes when checking code into Subversion'''

The string should be descriptive enough to place the changes in
the context of the ticket(s) the changes are associated with. This can be
implicit through the wording, explicity by referring to the ticket(s) using
wiki formatting in the subversion check-in string or both. We do not place
any restrictions on what this text includes. You can include any text you
wish as long as it includes information that associates it with the ticket.

'''Form and work from branches as necessary, but for short periods of time only (30 days or less).'''

Branches are transitory and formed with the intent
to merge back to the trunk at a point in the near future.

== Coding Rules ==

'''Follow Java coding conventions as outlined below.'''

Adherence to the conventions outlined below are required. In addition,
developers should attempt to adhere to the coding conventions outlined by
Sun Microsystems.
* Package names are all lower case and are prefixed by "org.opendap."
* Class names are nouns in !UpperCamelCase
* Interfaces are in !UpperCamelCase
* Methods names are verbs in lowerCamelCase
* Instances of classes are in lowerCamelCase
* Constants are all uppercase with words separated by an underscore</text>
      <sha1>dosy2w8bu4dkgpi8zvlminjxaff7d46</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
