<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.11.xsd" version="0.11" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>OPeNDAP Documentation</sitename>
    <dbname>wikidb</dbname>
    <base>https://docs.opendap.org/index.php/Home</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.38.4</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">OPeNDAP Documentation</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">OPeNDAP Documentation talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>Compression</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>323</id>
    <revision>
      <id>2266</id>
      <timestamp>2008-06-25T16:42:20Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jimg</username>
        <id>3</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>New page: We work with a few groups that do a fair amount of experimental compression depending on the type of data they are using. This made me think about how OPeNDAP handles compression. Here's w...</comment>
      <origin>2266</origin>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text bytes="2480" sha1="ifang8vmvdlxivwnw4a3tcka9z8n93h" xml:space="preserve">We work with a few groups that do a fair amount of experimental compression depending on the type of data they are using. This made me think about how OPeNDAP handles compression. Here's what I found in the DAP 4.0 spec:

'''Compression''': DAP clients MUST be provided a way indicate to a server that they are able to process compressed responses. A server MAY compress a response ONLY if a client has indicated that it can process the compressed response. A server is NEVER under any obligation to compress a response. Support for particular compression algorithms is specific to the transport protocol.

Have you thought at all about allowing the client to indicate the kinds of compression it can accept and the server specifying what kind of compression it is using with a given response? That would add a lot of flexibility. Does the last sentence above mean that how the compression stuff is handled is defined in the specs for each particular transport protocol?

I think something about multiple compression algorithms should be said in the above section so that the various transport protocol specific specs will all deal with that issue. Maybe something like:

'''Compression''': DAP clients MUST be provided a way indicate to a server whether the client supports any compression algorithms and which ones it supports. A server MAY compress a response ONLY if a client has indicated that it can process the compressed response. A server MUST indicate the compression algorithm used to compress the response. A server is NEVER under and obligation to compress a response.

I know this complicates things a bit but I really think it will be a useful feature. What do you think?

''EthanDavis - 17 Mar 2004''

Is there some standardized way to describe compression algorithms?  Without such an accept list of compression type names I think this  opens up a nasty can of worms... 

''NathanPotter - 17 Mar 2004''

I agree there needs to be a list of defined compression types but I'm not sure it has to be a standardized way. I do think it is important that it be extensible. For example, the folks we work with who do compression are developing new algorithms that they might want to use.

Perhaps each transport protocol needs to list the names of current standard compression techniques but allow names not on the list. OGC WCS must do something similar with return formats; GeoTIFF and HDF are the suggested formats but others are allowed.

''EthanDavis - 20 Mar 2004''</text>
      <sha1>ifang8vmvdlxivwnw4a3tcka9z8n93h</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
